Let's talk agent skills.
Skills are portable on-demand extensions for AI agents.
Think Neo from the Matrix downloading Kung Fu without the minor issue of forcing a footlong spike
right into the skull.
Skills have been incredibly popular due to their simplicity and their economic token use.
But this research on software engineering skills found that four out of five agent skills
yielded zero improvement over not using a skill at all.
In fact, some skills are more banana peel than power up mushroom,
making the agent even worse than not using a skill at all.
It's like if Neo's new skill hadn't improved his fighting,
but given him imbalance problems or cause them to directly punch himself repeatedly in the face.
Having said all that, some skills are incredibly powerful.
One paper found that a small model with the right skill can be the frontier model without one,
which has some pretty big cost implications.
So what separates a skill that actually boosts performance from one that just
clodders the context window?
We'll talk about exactly that and how you can write better skills in the
this video. Let's start by discussing why skills exist, which is to extend generative models.
Yes, these models know a lot, but even the best ones can't know everything, because nothing can
is just not how knowledge works. First of all, models can't get access to every piece of private
information in the world, like my private diary entry from 1999, anointing the Phantom Menace to be the
best movie ever. And second, knowledge changes over time, like how we now know the Phantom Menace to be only the
second best movie ever, right behind Morbius. But instead of admitting uncertainty, models still
hallucinate with the energy of a random red to argue with the Nobel laureate. In agent form,
where models are given tools to interact with the world, this means that an agent can
happily delete your work or production database, while explaining in great excruciating detail exactly
why that was the right thing to do, at least right before they turn around, then profusely
apologize for their mistake. One obvious solution is to stuff the agent with everything that it might need,
whether it be a long prompt, tools or MCPs. But unfortunately,
more context isn't free. Sure, context windows are getting larger,
but every token that you add competes with the actual task, and researchers have found
that unnecessary context actively degrades performance. This is why Anthropic built
agent skills as an open standard. What makes skills different from other solutions
is this idea of progressive disclosure. Skills allow you to organize the information
that it might or might not need into packages, which can then be loaded only as it needs
it. For an agent, this means a far more efficient, focused use of its context window. And for the user,
faster inference, lower compute, and better results. All these benefits and the fact that skills
are just text files led to rapid, broad adoption, leading to a huge range of public skills to choose from.
This also meant that researchers are able to dig in and evaluate skills in detail. The resulting benchmarks,
skills bench and SW skills bench converge on these findings. One, longer skills
skills generally perform poorly when compared to focused, concise skills. And two, narrow,
specialized skills that fill real knowledge gaps help the most, like those that relate concrete
procedures or domain-specific ones. And three, a smaller model like Anthropics Haiku with a well-ridden
skill can beat a frontier model like Opus with no skill. Let's spend a minute on that one,
because it's a big deal for your bottom line.
In case you don't know, Haiku is the smallest model in Anthropics product suite.
Smaller models like Haiku are cheaper and faster, but they're also less capable. Think of
it like a fast food line cook versus a Michelin-start chef. But under the right circumstances,
the line cook can provide great value. For example, if you give that line cook the exact recipe
and the right equipment, they'll outperform a chef cooking blinding a tent. That's exactly what
research has found here. Haiku with well-written skills, outperformed opus on specific
specific tasks. This is a big finding given the cost differences between a frontier model
and the smaller one, and even the possibility of running local models. It's a reminder that
you don't always need the latest or the biggest model. Size does matter, sure, but, you know,
it's not, it's not everything. So far, we've talked about the impact of good skills. In other
words, the kung fu kind of useful skill that elevates the agent, not the detrimental kind that might
cause the agent to punch itself in the face. So what makes something a good skill? Like,
Luckily for us, the research gives us pretty good guidance on this.
So let's start with the part that might matter the most, which is triggering.
Remember that skills rely on progressive disclosure. This means that an agent must actively
choose to read the skill to make use of it. And since an agent can only see the skill description
entitled to make this choice, a skill with a poorly written description is unlikely to trigger
at the right time. You know, much like how you wouldn't have clicked on this video if we had
called it JP Stairs Blank Leans De Void for an hour.
With a poor description, the skill won't be loaded at the agent's time of need.
Worse, it might be loaded for the wrong job, like how if you did want to watch me
stay a blankly at the screen for an hour, you'd be very disappointed at this video right now.
The recommendations for skill descriptions are to keep it short but specific and to name concrete
trigger scenarios. So don't write cryptic descriptions like helps with documents,
which could both trigger on everything or trigger on nothing, depending on what the agent feels
like. Instead, write something more specific and precise like, use this skill whenever
the user wants to create, read, edit or manipulate word documents. You can read this and concretely
tell whether something is in or if something is out. That means the agent can trigger it at the
right time and only at the right time. Once you've got the skill to trigger, then you can worry about
making the contents useful without being excessive. Progressive disclosure isn't just limited
to the idea of will this skill trigger. The skill package itself can have multiple
documents with the body referring to additional references. And this kind of nested structure is
really helpful because of the finding that excessive length is detrimental. The recommendation
is to keep domain skill.md to a maximum length of 500 lines or so. Note that this doesn't put a limit
on the total amount of information because of the ability to refer to more files. So for example,
Elastic's own Kibana dashboard skill comes with over a dozen additional files, including
JavaScript code, API references, and example JSON files.
So it's just like a choose-your-own-adventure book, if perhaps the adventure was the
wonderful journey of vibe coding. In other words, only include the required information
for the job. Before writing any line, ask yourself, would the agent screw this up without being
told? So don't explain the obvious, like what a database is. Definitely don't write follow best
practices. That's not guidance, that's a fortune cookie. What you should write is the stuff
specific to your context that prevents failures. Here are some examples in Anthropos,
its own skills creator skill. And look at the specificity here of lines like,
save this data immediately to timing.json in the run directory. This is the only opportunity to capture
this data. Or the grading.jason expectations array must use the fields, text, past, and evidence,
not name, met details, or other variants. You can almost feel the original errors that inspired
these lines when they try to do the job before they wrote those skills. So when you're writing
skills use the energy of old biff from back to the future, passing on his wisdom to a younger
biff before the mistakes. And here's a surprising one. In one study, skills with executable
code examples triple the pass rates of not having skills. Even in the age of vibe coding,
the vibes vibe better when they're less vibes and more code. Another reminder that where
specificity is available, you should use it. Speaking of specificity, this applies to versions and software
libraries. So version mismatched skills were a notable failure mode that made agents worse.
So don't write React Project if you can write React 18 with TypeScript and Vite instead.
Quick recap on skill writing, tight descriptions, compact structure, concrete
code examples, and exact versioning. Master those and you'll be closer to a skill that
actually triggers and delivers. Let me show you what this looks like in practice. I've been
using a skill for ESQL query generation, which is Elastic's newer query language.
It's a textbook case for a skill because ESQL is new enough that models don't have deep training
data on it. And the name is similar enough to all the Elastic Query DSL or even SQL, that models
confidently write the wrong thing. You can see here that without the skill, the model mixed
up ESQL with some other syntax, creating a wrong command and inventing functions. But with it
loaded, the model writes fluent, correct ESQL. That's the line cook with the recipe right there,
versus the confused chef without proper instructions and tools.
So how do you prove that a skill is actually helpful and not just punching your agent in the face?
Let's say that you've written a skill flogging data into your preferred observability stack,
like Elasticsearch. Step 1, compare the outputs. Take 5 or 10 real tasks and run them with and without
the skill. The results are your quality signal, like whether the apps were correctly wired,
and whether the outputs were passed correctly. Step 2, check your fits if it's been triggering.
Throw 20 different prompts at your agent, some logging related, and some not, and record the results.
If it's triggering on research this problem or write the read me, your description needs work.
Similarly, if it's not triggering on set up logging for this AI agent, it probably needs work.
Now, here's something that I found really interesting. Apparently, LLM generated skills are generally not
helpful at all. And if you think about it, it kind of makes intuitive sense, right?
skills work because they encode expertise the model doesn't have. So asking a model to generate
its own skill is a little bit like getting a new grad to write their own onboarding. At best it's
going to be a lot of things that they already know, and at worst, they'll pass on incorrect
information to the next person. What you should do instead is to start from real work and write
skills for patterns of errors that you observe. Or better yet, write the evaluation tasks
first and then write the skill to improve on those evaluations. It's also good practice to
to periodically evaluate those skills over time. Models and harnesses will get better,
and your preferences will change. And you don't always have to start from scratch either. There's
already a huge ecosystem of skills out there to choose from. I've been writing my own skills too.
I'm working on skills to help me generate visual explainers or playing tutorials,
although I've yet to find a skill far outsourcing this job to an agent so I can go and play
video games. You know, I'd love to hear about your favorite skills,
whether you wrote them to yourself or if it's a public skill.
And also, tell us about your experience creating your own skills if you did,
what principles or tips do you find useful, and maybe which ones you don't find so useful?
You can chime in in in the comments below, which happens to be right below the like button.
That's it for me, links to the resources are in the description, so drop your favorite
skills in the comments, and I'll see you next time.